Lewis Tappan Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Lewis Tappan Papers 1809-1903 1809-1872
(bulk 1809-1872)
MSS42317
Tappan, Lewis, 1788-1873
5,200 items
15 containers
10 linear feet
7 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Abolitionist, merchant, and publisher. Correspondence, journals, and other papers reflecting Tappan's interests in abolition, African American education, religion, and his business ventures.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848--Correspondence.; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848.; Aspinwall family--Correspondence.; Aspinwall family.; Birney, James Gillespie, 1792-1857--Correspondence.; Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895--Correspondence.; Finney, Charles G., 1792-1875--Correspondence.; Garrison, William Lloyd, 1805-1879--Correspondence.; Gates, Seth Merrill, 1800-1877--Correspondence.; Hastings, Samuel D. (Samuel Dexter), 1816-1903--Correspondence.; Jay, William, 1789-1858--Correspondence.; Leavitt, Joshua, 1794-1873--Correspondence.; Phelps, Amos A. (Amos Augustus), 1805-1847--Correspondence.; Sedgwick, Theodore, 1780-1839--Correspondence.; Shipherd, John Jay, 1802-1844--Correspondence.; Sturge, Joseph, 1793-1859--Correspondence.; Tappan family--Correspondence.; Tappan family.; Tappan, Arthur, 1786-1865--Correspondence.; Tappan, Benjamin, 1773-1857--Correspondence.; Tappan, Lewis, 1788-1873.; Weld, Theodore Dwight, 1803-1895.; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892--Correspondence.
Organizations
American and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society.; American Bible Society.; American Colonization Society.; American Missionary Association.; Amistad (Schooner); General Anti-slavery Convention (2nd: 1843: London, England); Liberty Party (U.S.: 1840-1848); Mercantile Agency (New York, N.Y.); Oberlin College.; Union Missionary Society (U.S.)
Subjects
African Americans--Colonization--Africa.; African Americans--Education.; Antislavery movements--Periodicals.; Antislavery movements--Societies, etc.; Antislavery movements--United States.; Antislavery movements.; Calvinism.; Colonization--Societies, etc.; Commerce--Periodicals.; Credit bureaus--New York (State)--New York.; Credit ratings--United States.; Freedmen--Colonization--Africa.; Missions--Periodicals.; Missions--Societies, etc.; Missions.; Religion.; Slave rebellions--United States.; Slavery and the church.; Slavery--United States.; Slavery.; Trials (Mutiny)--United States.; Unitarianism.
Places
Africa--Colonization.; New York (N.Y.)--Religion--19th century.; Texas--Annexation to the United States.; United States--Religion--19th century.; United States--Social conditions--19th century.
Titles
American missionary.; Bible--Publication and distribution--Societies, etc.; National era (Washington, D.C.); New York journal of commerce (New York, N.Y.)
Occupations
Abolitionists.; Merchants.; Publishers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Lewis Tappan, abolitionist, merchant, and publisher, were acquired by the Library of Congress from various sources, 1928-1958. The bulk of the material was given by his granddaughter, Anna Hulett. Additional items were purchased by the Library in 1982 and 2014.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Lewis Tappan are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on seven reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Online Content
Selected documents from the Lewis Tappan Papers are available on the Library of Congress website at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/eadmss.ms010139.001.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1788, May 23 Born, Northhampton, Mass.
1813 Married Susan Aspinwall (died 1853)
1828 circa 1837 Partner with brother Arthur and credit manager, Arthur Tappan & Co., silk jobbers in New York, N.Y.
1828 1831 Owned and published Journal of Commerce, New York, N.Y.
1833 One of the founders of the New York Anti-Slavery Society and the American Anti-Slavery Society
1839 1841 Member of the committee that undertook to secure the freedom of the captives on the slave ship Amistad
1840 Founder and first treasurer, American and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society
1841 1849 Established and operated the Mercantile Agency, the first commercial credit-rating agency in America, under the firm name of Lewis Tappan & Co.
1843 Attended General Anti-slavery Convention, London, England
1846 A founder of the American Missionary Association
1850, ca. Participated, after passage of the Fugitive Slave Law, in “underground railroad” activities
1854 Married Mrs. Sarah J. Davis
1855 Joined the American Abolition Society
1870 Published The Life of Arthur Tappan. New York: Hurd and Houghton
1873, June 21 Died, Brooklyn, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Lewis Tappan (1788-1873) span the years 1809-1903, with the bulk dating from 1809 to 1872. The collection consists of correspondence, letterbooks, journals, notebooks, clippings, photocopies, notes, and miscellaneous other items. The journals and notebooks, which date from 1841 to 1869, are replete with information concerning Tappan’s activities in the antislavery movement and contribute as well to an understanding of his private life, particularly his religious views. The collection is organized in the following series: Journals and Notebooks, Correspondence, Miscellany, and Additions.
The bulk of the correspondence in the Lewis Tappan papers is made up of copies of his outgoing letters, ranging in date from 1812 to 1870. Legibility of many of these copies is poor, and there are a number of gaps in the chronology. Nine of the volumes include indexes to correspondents. Incoming correspondence, although limited in quantity, covers the period 1809-1871. Subject matter throughout Tappan’s correspondence strongly reflects his interest in antislavery activities and his participation in organizations that promoted abolition.
Tappan’s exposure to Calvinist and Unitarian theology is reflected in his journals by comments on ministers and the themes of their sermons. Also evident in the journals, which contain numerous newspaper clippings, and in his correspondence, is Tappan’s involvement in promoting his ideas through Bible, tract, peace, abolition, and missionary societies, and through Sunday schools, free churches, charitable organizations, political parties, and newspapers. Prominent among the organizations represented are the American and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society, the American Bible Society, the American Colonization Society, the American Missionary Association, the Union Missionary Society, and the Liberty Party. The New York Journal of Commerce, the National Era, and the American Missionary are among the publications with which Tappan was involved. Slavery, colonization, education of African Americans, and the role of the Christian in the abolition movement dominate the writings dating from 1836. Some of the leading issues discussed are the annexation of Texas and the moves taken for the release from custody of the African captives who had mutinied aboard the Spanish schooner Amistad. Of special interest is Tappan’s journal of the General Anti-slavery Convention of 1843 in London, England.
A small portion of the collection deals with Tappan’s business ventures, particularly his Mercantile Agency, the first commercial credit-rating agency in the United States. Throughout the papers there is documentation of routine family activities of the various members of the Tappan family, as well as of their interaction on matters of mutual concern, particularly where business, religion, and abolition were involved.
Prominent correspondents include John Quincy Adams, James Gillespie Birney, Frederick Douglass, William Lloyd Garrison, Seth Merrill Gates, Samuel D. Hastings, William Jay, Joshua Leavitt, Amos A. Phelps, Theodore Sedgwick, Joseph Sturge, and John Greenleaf Whittier. Lewis Tappan’s brothers, Benjamin and Arthur, are well represented in the collection as well as other members of the Tappan and Aspinwall families.
In addition to original manuscripts, photocopies of Tappan items in other repositories—notably from papers in the Oberlin College Library—are present in the collection. Most of these copies fall between 1831 and 1841, and consist of letters of Arthur and Lewis Tappan to John J. Shipherd, Charles G. Finney, and Samuel D. Hastings. They deal mainly with the Tappan brothers’ involvement in, and financial support of, religious movements in New York City and at Oberlin College.
Miscellaneous items include John Quincy Adams’s holograph draft of a legal brief pleading for release of the Amistad captives, autobiographical notes, genealogical material on the Tappan and Aspinwall families, and a lecture by Theodore Weld. Writings, notes, and other miscellaneous items relating to slavery include a list of articles on emancipation by Lewis Tappan, a list of antislavery hymns, a copy of a deed of manumission, an article by Ansel Bascom, and materials on the expurgation of references to slavery in published works.
The Additions consist of a letter of 1857 by Tappan to Henry A. Miles reflecting on his religious beliefs, and a letter of 1847 by Tappan expressing condolonces to Eliza Scott on the death of her husband, Orange Scott.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Journals and Notebooks, 1814-1869
Correspondence, 1809-1872
Miscellany, circa 1839-1903
Additions, 1847-1857
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 16,431
- Journals and Notebooks, 1814-1869 (Box 1-2A, Reel 1-2)
  Volumes containing entries of activities, clippings, and miscellaneous information.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1814 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1816, Oct. 22-1820, Mar. 6 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1820, Mar. 16-1824, Oct. 21 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1824, Oct. 22-1828, Feb. 15 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1828, Feb. 16-1829, Nov. 6 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - 1836, Feb. 23-1838, Aug. 30 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - 1838, Aug. 31-1840, Jun. 10 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - 1840, Nov. 8-1841, Aug. 10 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - 1843 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - 1851, May 17-1853, Jun. 30 (Box 2A, Reel 2)
  - 1853, Jul. 1-1855, Apr. 18 (Box 2A, Reel 2)
  - 1855, Apr. 19-1869, May 23 (Box 2A, Reel 2)
- Correspondence, 1809-1872 (Box 2A-14, Reel 2-7)
  - Letterbooks, 1812-1870 (Box 2A-13, Reel 2-5)
    Arranged chronologically with alphabetical indexes in the front of vols. 3-11.
    - 1812, Oct. 3-1827, Jan. 11 (Box 2A, Reel 2)
    - 1839, Oct. 5-1840, Sept. 7 (Box 3, Reel 2)
    - 1842, Aug. 24-1844, Apr. 25 (Box 4, Reel 3)
    - 1844, Apr. 30-1846, Mar. 10 (Box 5, Reel 3)
    - 1846, Mar. 10-1847, Nov. 4 (Box 6, Reel 3)
    - 1847, Nov. 4-1852, Jun. 30 (Box 7, Reel 4)
    - 1852, Feb. 23-1857, Dec. 24 (Box 8, Reel 4)
    - 1854, Nov. 8-1855, Jul. 13 (Box 9, Reel 5)
    - 1855, Jul. 13-1856, Feb. 28 (Box 10, Reel 5)
    - 1863, Jun. 16-1866, Jun. 10 (Box 11, Reel 5)
    - 1870, Nov. 12-Dec. 29 (Box 12, Reel 5)
  - General, 1809-1871 (Box 13, Reel 6)
    Mostly letters to Lewis Tappan.
    - 1809-1871, undated, (22 folders) (Box 13, Reel 6)
  - Photocopies, 1838-1872 (Box 14, Reel 7)
    Mostly letters by Lewis and Arthur Tappan from collections of papers in the Oberlin College Library, Oberlin, Ohio.
    - 1838-1872, undated, (4 folders) (Box 13, Reel 7)
- Miscellany, circa 1839-1903 (Box 14, Reel 7)
  Autobiographical and genealogical notes, clippings, scrapbook, lecture, John Quincy Adams’s brief on the Amistad case, and other items.
  - American Anti-Slavery Society, clippings, 1840-1843, undated (Box 14, Reel 7)
  - Amistad case, including John Quincy Adams’s legal brief, 1839-1841, undated (Box 14, Reel 7)
  - Biographical and genealogical material (Box 14, Reel 7)
    - Chronological résumé of Lewis Tappan’s life from 1802 to 1871, written by himself (Box 14, Reel 7)
    - History of the Tappan family and short autobiography of Lewis Tappan (Box 14, Reel 7)
    - Tappan and Aspinwall families, photocopies of genealogical charts, notes, and pamphlets (Box 14, Reel 7)
    - Tappan family scrapbook, circa 1842-1903 (Box 14, Reel 7)
  - Index to narrative of Lewis Tappan (Box 14, Reel 7)
  - Name and address book, 1847-1852 (Box 14, Reel 7)
  - New York draft riot, account [1863?] (facsimile) (Box 14, Reel 7)
  - “Truth’s Hindrances,” a lecture by Theodore D. Weld (Box 14, Reel 7)
  - Writings, notes, and other items on slavery (Box 14, Reel 7)
- Additions, 1847-1857 (Box 14, not filmed)
  Correspondence.
  Arranged in order of processing date.
  - 2010 Addition (Box 14, not filmed)
    - Letter to Henry A. Miles, 1857 (Box 14, not filmed)
  - 2020 Addition (Box 14, not filmed)
    - Letter to Eliza Scott, 1847 (Box 14, not filmed)